Guide to the Park Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Park family papers
1701-1929
MS 384
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
6.5
(16 boxes, 1 folio)
The Park family papers are composed of correspondence and other papers of Park family members and of correspondence and other documents collected and preserved by Park family members for their autograph or historical value. The papers include six volumes of mounted autograph items as well as unbound documents of American and European authors, scientists, military leaders, statesmen, and clergymen. The papers include a large collection of documents relating to the history, faculty, and administration of Phillips Academy, Andover, Massachusetts and of the Andover Theological Seminary. Particularly numerous are the personal and professonal papers of Eliphalet Pearson. The papers also include numerous documents of John Hoff Duke of Charleston, South Carolina, as well as estate papers of Augustine Prevost and documents relating to the early history of Wrentham, Massachusetts. Papers of Park family members include intra-family correspondence and items of related Burr, Edwards, and Reeve family members. Marion Edwards Park's correspondence documents her college years at Bryn Mawr. Correspondence with M. Carey Thomas in the 1920s details the transition of leadership at the college.
Park family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gifts of Edwards Albert Park and Marion Edwards Park, 1935-1964.
Associated Materials
Associated material: Burr Family Papers (MS 303), (Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.)
Associated material: Reeve Family Papers (MS 686), (Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.)
Associated material: Jonathan Edwards Papers, (Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.)
Scope and Contents
The Park Family Papers are composed of correspondence and other papers of Park family members and of correspondence and other documents collected and preserved by Park family members for their autograph or historical value. The Park family is composed of several generations of clergymen and educators. Theologian and professor Edwards Amasa Park, his son William Edwards Park, and his granddaughter Bryn Mawr College President Marion Edwards Park are represented in the papers. In addition the papers contain letters and papers of Anna Maria Edwards Park, the wife of Edwards Amasa Park and great-granddaughter of Jonathan Edwards, and of related members of the Burr, Edwards, and Reeve families. Also represented in the papers are Sara Billings Edwards, the wife of William Edwards Park, and her family. Her father was the theologian and editor Bela Bates Edwards and her mother was Jerusha William Billings, who conducted a school for girls in Andover, Massachusetts, and was the sister of Elizabeth Storrs Billings Mead, the president of Mount Holyoke College from 1890 to 1901.
In addition to the family materials the papers contain a large collection of documents including correspondence, minutes, voting records, reports, and printed material relating to the history, faculty, and administration of Phillips Academy, Andover, Massachusetts, and of Andover Theological Seminary. Particularly numerous are the personal and professional papers of Eliphalet Pearson, the academy's first principal and seminary founder, and of Samuel Farrar. The papers also include numerous documents of John Hoff Duke of Charleston, South Carolina, estate papers of Augustine Prevost, papers relating to the early history of Wrentham, Massachusetts, and six autograph albums containing letters and documents signed by American and European authors, scientists, statesmen, and clergymen.
Edwards Albert Park and Marion Edwards Park donated their family's papers to the Yale University Library between 1935 and 1960. An inventory of the papers received through 1954 is included in this register as Appendices A and B. This inventory describes all material in Edwards Albert and Marion Edwards Park's donation, including some material transferred to other collections. Most though not all material relating to Burr, Reeve, and Edwards family members is now found in either the Burr Family Papers (MS 303) or the Reeve Family Papers (MS 686) in the Manuscripts and Archives Department or in the Jonathan Edwards Papers in the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library.
The Park Family Papers are arranged in two series: I. CORRESPONDENCE AND PAPERS, 1715-1903 and II. FAMILY PAPERS, 1701-1929.
Both series contain papers of Park family members and papers collected and preserved by Park family members, though Series II contains a higher proportion of family papers. The contents of Series I are thoroughly indexed in Appendix A, which is arranged alphabetically by personal or corporate name, or Appendix B, which is organized by topic. Materials described on one list are not listed on the other, and most items in Series II are not included on these lists.
Series I is arranged in chronological order. The majority of the materials in boxes 1-4 relate to the personal life and professional career of Eliphalet Pearson. These materials are detailed in Appendix B. A few additional letters to Pearson are listed in Appendix A. Pearson's correspondence, as well as that of Samuel Farrar (boxes 5 and 6), concerns Phillips Academy and Andover Theological Seminary. Topics and frequent correspondents include Leonard Woods, Jedidiah Morse, Samuel Phillips, Moses Stuart, Samuel Abbot, Jonathan French, Benjamin B. Wisner, and several benefactors of the schools. In addition the series includes Pearson sermons and petitions, subscription lists, organizational papers, memoranda, reports, minutes, wills and statistics relating to the schools. Additional Pearson correspondence and papers concern the American Society for the Education of Pious Youth for the Ministry, Harvard University, and the Massachusetts Society for Promoting Christian Knowledge. Other correspondents include Pearson's first and second wives, his father-in-law Edward A. Holyoke, and his son Henry B. Pearson.
Scattered through boxes 1-5 are additional items not related to Pearson, the academy, or the seminary. There are numerous documents relating to Augustine Prevost and his estate. There are also letters, notes, and sermons concerning Nathanael Emmons and Samuel Hopkins, perhaps collected by Edwards Amasa Park when editing the collected works of these men. Several early documents relate to Wrentham, Massachusetts in the 1700s.
Boxes 6 through 8 contain letters to Park family members and to Bela Bates Edwards. A few concern the editing of Bibliotheca Sacra and some recall trips to Europe. The letters form no continuous correspondence but rather appear to have been preserved for their autograph value. Many of these letters are listed in either Appendix A or B. These boxes also contain the collection of documents relating to John Hoff Duke of Charleston, South Carolina, which is described in Appendix B. There is also correspondence of Eliphalet Pearson's children, some of which is with Edwards Amasa Park, concerning publication of a memoir or biography of their father and the history of Andover Theological Seminary.
Boxes 9 and 10 contain six volumes of mounted autographs as well as a few loose items. The volumes are thoroughly indexed in Appendix A by the name of the creator of the letter or document. Appendix A is annotated with volume and page numbers for nearly all items found in the volumes. The volumes are arranged by subject or geographic area and include autographs by authors, clergymen, American statesmen, British and continental scientists and academicians, and American Revolutionary War figures and presidents.
Series II, FAMILY PAPERS, includes correspondence, notes, writings, memorabilia, and printed material organized by the name of individual family members. The materials for all family members are fragmentary and in most instances there are only one or two exchanges in a folder. The correspondence arranged under any individual's name includes both incoming and outgoing letters.
The largest quantity of material in the series is that of Edwards Amasa Park. It includes family correspondence, lectures, sermons, notes by others on Park's lectures, writings of others, and additional material relating to Eliphalet Pearson, Andover Theological Seminary, and topics of Edwards Amasa Park's or William Edwards Park's research. Some of this material is indexed in either Appendix A or B.
There is also a sizeable quantity of material relating to Marion Edwards Park in the series. It includes several folders of letters to her mother Sara Billings Edwards Park including those from her undergraduate years at Bryn Mawr and from her studies abroad. There are also four folders of letters from M. Carey Thomas which document Bryn Mawr's offer of its presidency to Park and the transition of leadership in the early 1920s. Thomas's lengthy letters discuss the future of various academic departments and faculty appointments.
Correspondence of William Edwards Park and his wife and family portrays the life of a Congregational minister in Gloversville, New York. The series also includes correspondence of related Billings, Edwards, and Mead family members, travel letters of various Park family members, Timothy Edwards's letterbook (1797-1813), and notebooks kept by students on lectures by Tapping Reeve and James Gould at the Litchfield Law School. Folder 245 contains a list documenting Edwards Albert Park's sizeable donation of books by and about Jonathan Edwards and the Congregational Church in New England to the Yale Library in 1912.
Arrangement
The Park Family Papers are arranged in two series: I. CORRESPONDENCE AND PAPERS, 1715-1903 and II. FAMILY PAPERS, 1701-1929.
Biographical / Historical
The Park family is composed of several generations of clergymen and educators. Edwards Amasa Park was a theologian and professor at Andover Theological Seminary (1836-1881). His son William Edwards Park was a minister of the Congregational Church in Gloversville, New York, and his granddaughter Marion Edwards Park was president of Bryn Mawr College from 1922 to 1942. Edwards Amasa Park's wife was Anna Maria Edwards, a great-granddaughter of Jonathan Edwards. She was also related to members of the Burr and Reeve families. William Edwards Park's wife, Sara Billings Edwards, was the daughter of theologian and editor Bela Bates Edwards and Jerusha William Billings, who conducted a school for girls in Andover, Massachusetts, and was the sister of Elizabeth Storrs Billings Mead, the president of Mount Holyoke College from 1890 to 1901.
WILLIAM EDWARDS PARK, only son of Rev. Edwards Amasa Park, D.D., LL.D., (B.A. Brown 1826), who was Professor in Andover Theological Seminary for forty-five years, was born in Andover, Mass., July 1, 1837. His mother was Ann Maria (Edwards) Park, a great-granddaughter of Jonathan Edwards. He was prepared for college at Phillips Academy in his native town, and was a member of the class of 1860 for three years, joining '61 the last term of junior year.
After graduation he studied at home until March, 1862, when he went to St. Helena Island, S. C., as a member of the first party sent from the North by the Educational Commission for Freedmen. After four months in this work he engaged in teaching and studying law in New York City, and in the fall of 1863 entered the Andover Theological Seminary, from which he graduated in 1867. During this time, however, he spent ten months in Nashville, Tenn., as a delegate of the United States Christian Commission, and in 1865 co-operated in raising funds to rebuild Phillips Academy, which had been destroyed by fire.
He was licensed to preach in December, 1866, and devoted thirty-six years of his life to the ministry in two pastorates. He was ordained and installed pastor of the Central Congregational Church of Lawrence, Mass., November 13, 1867, and remained there eight years. June 21, 1876, he was installed over the Congregational Church in Gloversville, N. Y., where he continued in active service until 1904, and was pastor emeritus at the time of his death. The twenty-fifth anniversary of his settlement furnished an occasion for voicing the warm appreciation of the church and of the town of his achievements. His church under his influence felt a keen interest in education, and an unusually large proportion of the young men have come to Yale. He devoted much care to the foundation and development of the Public Library.
In addition to his local work he had many wider interests. He was moderator of the New York State Association of Congregational Churches on three occasions and several times of the Hudson River Association. In 1885 and at each subsequent council until 1908 he was a delegate to the National Council of Congregational Churches. For twenty-five years he was a corporate member of the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions, and for twenty years was a member of the New York State Home Missionary Committee and state representative of the Church Building Society. He was president of the Phillips (Andover) Academy Alumni Association, and in 1903 was elected president of the Yale Alumni Association of Fulton and Montgomery Counties, N.Y. He received the honorary degree of Doctor of Divinity from Marietta College in 1888.
He made seven long sojourns abroad, and had been an extensive traveler. Since 1904 he had resided in Oberlin, O., engaged in literary work. In 1907 he became associate editor of the Bibliotheca Sacra, of which his eminent father was editor from 1844 to 1884. He also wrote many articles on various subjects for newspapers, magazines, and encyclopedias, and delivered a large number of public lectures. In June, 1878, he read a paper on the "Earlier Annals of Phillips Academy," at its centennial anniversary.
Dr. Park died suddenly at his home in Oberlin, May 19, 1910, in the 73rd year of his age.
He married March 4, 1874, Sara Billings, daughter of Professor Bela B. Edwards, D.D. (B.A. Amherst 1824), of Andover Seminary, and Jerusha W. (Billings) Edwards, who survives him. Their daughter graduated from Bryn Mawr College in 1898, and their son from the Academical Department of Yale in 1900.
From Yale University Obituary Record.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Other Finding Aids
For a listing of correspondents, printed materials, and papers, please consult the Collection Inventory.
Congregationalism; Education; Families; Religion -- 19th century; Theology, Doctrinal -- Massachusetts; Voyages and travels; Women -- Education; Andover (Mass.); Europe -- Description and travel; New England; Wrentham (Mass.: Town); Autographs; Sermons; Clergy; College presidents; Educators; Abbot, Samuel; Duke, John Hoff; Edwards, B. B. (Bela Bates), 1802-1852; Edwards, Jerusha Williams Billings, 1809-1896; Edwards, Timothy, 1738-1813; Emmons, Nathanael, 1745-1840; Farrar, Samuel, 1773-1864; French, Jonathan, 1740-1809; Hopkins, Samuel, 1721-1803; Morse, Jedidiah, 1761-1826; Park, Edwards A. (Edwards Albert), 1877-1969; Park, Edwards Amasa, 1808-1900; Park, Marion Edwards, 1875-1960; Park, Sara Billings Edwards, d. 1913; Park, William Edwards, 1837-1910; Pearson, Eliphalet, 1752-1826; Pearson, Henry Bromfield, 1795-1867; Phillips, Samuel, 1752-1802; Reeve, Tapping, 1744-1823; Stuart, Moses, 1780-1852; Thomas, M. Carey (Martha Carey), 1857-1935; Wisner, Benjamin B. (Benjamin Blydenburg), 1794-1835; Woods, Leonard, 1774-1854; Park family; American Society for Educating Pious Youth for the Gospel Ministry; Andover Theological Seminary; Bryn Mawr College; Harvard University ( History); Litchfield Law School; Massachusetts Society for Promoting Christian Knowledge; Phillips Academy
- Correspondence and Papers, 1715-1903; Series I; 4.0' (10 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series is arranged in two sections: General and Autograph albums. The materials in General are arranged in chronological order. The volumes in Autograph albums are in order by volume number, with loose autographs placed at the end.
  - General
    - 1715 - 1789 (Box 1, Folder 1-15)
    - 1790 - 1805 (Box 2, Folder 16-29)
    - 1806 - 1812 (Box 3, Folder 30-46)
    - 1813 - 1817 September (Box 4, Folder 47-61)
    - 1817 October - 1826 September (Box 5, Folder 62-78)
    - 1826 October - 1839 (Box 6, Folder 79-94)
    - 1840 - 1889 (Box 7, Folder 95-110)
    - 1890 - 1903 (Box 8, Folder 111-113)
    - undated (Box 8, Folder 114-116)
  - Autograph albums
    - Volume 1: Authors (Box 9, Folder 117)
    - Volume 2: American statesmen (Box 9, Folder 118)
    - Volume 3: British (Box 9, Folder 119)
    - Volume 4: Clergymen, etc. (Box 10, Folder 120)
    - Volume 5: Continental (Box 10, Folder 121)
    - Volume 6: Revolution, Presidents (Box 10, Folder 122)
    - Loose autographs (Box 10, Folder 123)
- Family Papers, 1701-1929; Series II; 2.5' (6 boxes, 1 folio)
  This series is arranged in two sections: General and Oversize. The materials in each section are arranged in alphabetical order by name of individual.
  - General
    - Billings, Harriet S.
      - Correspondence
        - Edwards, Jerusha Williams Billings, undated (Box 11, Folder 124)
        - Park, William Edwards, 1876 (Box 11, Folder 125)
        - Unidentified, 1884 (Box 11, Folder 126)
    - Cornelius, Mrs. [Mary Ann Hooker?]
      - Correspondence, 1841 (Box 11, Folder 127)
    - Edwards, Elisha
      - Memorabilia: buttons from military coat, [pre-1812] (Box 11, Folder 128)
    - Edwards, George Herbert
      - Correspondence: Jackson, Charles, 1858-1862 (Box 11, Folder 129)
      - Letters concerning his death, 1863 (Box 11, Folder 130)
    - Edwards, Henry, 1798-1885
      General
      See: box 17, folder 251
    - Edwards, Jerusha Williams Billings, 1809-1896
      - Correspondence
        - Mead, Elizabeth Storrs Billings, and Harriet S. Billings, 1871-1872, 1884, undated (Box 11, Folder 131)
        - Park, Sara Billings Edwards, 1874-1884, undated (Box 11, Folder 132)
        - Miscellaneous family, 1884 (Box 11, Folder 133)
      - Note, 1838 (Box 11, Folder 134)
      - Obituary, 1896 (Box 11, Folder 134)
    - Edwards, Jonathan, 1703-1758
      See: box 17, folder 252
    - Edwards, Timothy, 1738-1813
      - Letterbook, 1797-1813 (Box 11, Folder 135)
    - Mead, Elizabeth Storrs Billings, 1832-1917
      - Correspondence
        - Park, Marion Edwards, 1902 (Box 11, Folder 136)
        - Park, Sara Billings Edwards, 1879, 1902 (Box 11, Folder 137)
    - Park, Agnes, 1845-
      - Correspondence
        - Park, Ann Maria Edwards, 1886 (Box 11, Folder 138)
        - Park, Sara Billings Edwards, [1885?] (Box 11, Folder 139)
        - Unidentified, 1874 (Box 11, Folder 140)
    - Park, Ann Maria Edwards
      - Correspondence
        - Park, Marion Edwards, undated (Box 11, Folder 141)
        - Park, Sara Billings Edwards, undated (Box 11, Folder 142)
        - Park, William Edwards, 1848-1850, undated (Box 11, Folder 143)
        - Unidentified, undated (Box 11, Folder 144)
    - Park, Calvin
      - Notebook, with notes on reading, 1813, 1844 (Box 11, Folder 145)
    - Park, Edwards Albert, 1877-1969
      - Correspondence
        - Park, Marion Edwards, 1895-1897, 1919, 1929 (Box 11, Folder 146)
        - Park, Sara Billings Edwards, 1900-1903 (Box 11, Folder 147)
      - Poem, undated (Box 11, Folder 148)
    - Park, Edwards Amasa, 1808-1900
      - Correspondence
        - Billings, Harriet S., 1895 (Box 12, Folder 149)
        - Edwards, Bela Bates, 1846 (Box 12, Folder 150)
        - Edwards, Jerusha Williams Billings, 1894-1895 (Box 12, Folder 151)
        - Park, Edwards Albert, 1885-1894 (Box 12, Folder 152)
        - Park, Marion Edwards, 1894 (Box 12, Folder 153)
        - Park, Sara Billings Edwards, 1870-1895, undated (Box 12, Folder 154)
        - Park, William Edwards, 1841-1947, undated (Box 12, Folder 155)
        - Wilkinson, Archibald, 1900 (Box 12, Folder 156)
      - Lecture, "Emmons as a Preacher,", undated (Box 12, Folder 157)
      - Lectures. [of EAP?] on the work of the ministry, undated (Box 12, Folder 158)
      - Lectures on systematic theology (Box 12, Folder 159)
        - Notebook kept by George Park Fisher, 1850-1851 (Box 12, Folder 159)
        - Notebook kept by James Barber Howard; with notes by Samuel Harris, subject "index to authorities in theology,", 1851-1852, undated (Box 12, Folder 159)
      - Ms account of the development of his antiquarian interests, 1875 (Box 12, Folder 160)
      - Newspaper clippings, 1882-1886, undated (Box 12, Folder 161)
      - Notes and documents
        - Re: Phillips Academy, Andover Theological Seminary and Eliphalet Pearson, undated (Box 12, Folder 162-164)
          General note
          See also: box 17, folder 253
        - Re: Massachusetts Society for Promoting Christian Knowledge; Phillips Academy, undated (Box 13, Folder 165)
        - Miscellaneous, 1806, undated (Box 13, Folder 166)
        - Fragments, undated (Box 13, Folder 167)
      - Poem, undated (Box 13, Folder 168)
      - Printed matter of Park and Eliphalet Pearson
        - Adelphi Theological Society, Edinburgh, 1807 (Box 13, Folder 169)
        - Amherst College, 1835 (Box 13, Folder 169)
        - Andover Theological Seminary, 1808-1856, undated (Box 13, Folder 169)
        - Brown, William Thurston, "Defense Before the Council in Reply to Charges of Heretical Teaching,", 1896 (Box 13, Folder 170)
        - Harvard College, 1807 (Box 13, Folder 170)
        - Massachusetts Society for Promoting Christian Knowledge, 1803 (Box 13, Folder 170)
        - Niles, Nathaniel, "A Letter to a Friend, ...,", 1809 (Box 13, Folder 170)
        - Pearson, Eliphalet, "A Sermon Delivered at the Ordination of the Rev. Ephraim Abbot...,", 1813 (Box 13, Folder 170)
        - Phillips Academy, undated (Box 13, Folder 170)
        - Princeton Theological Seminary, 1802, 1816 (Box 13, Folder 170)
        - Taggart, Samuel, "A Scriptural Vindication of the Doctrine of the Final Perseverance of all True Believers,", 1801 (Box 13, Folder 171)
        - Theremin, Franz, "The Awakening,", 1849 (Box 13, Folder 171)
        - Williams, Thomas, "A Sermon, on the Salvation of Sinners,", 1858 (Box 13, Folder 171)
        - Unidentified, "The Trial, Calvin and Hopkins versus the Bible and Common Sense,", 1819 (Box 13, Folder 171)
        - Miscellaneous, 1883, 1888, undated (Box 13, Folder 171)
          See also: box 17, folder 254
      - Sermons and lectures by Park and others, undated (Box 13, Folder 172-173)
      - Writings of others
        - [Burr, Aaron?]: "A Creed" (ms), undated (Box 13, Folder 174)
        - Emmons, Nathanael: ms sermon, preached at the installation of Calvin Park; printed essay, "Hopkinsian Calvinism,", 1826, 1858 (Box 13, Folder 175)
        - Hodge, Charles: ALS to Benjamin B. Wisner, 1823 (Box 13, Folder 176)
        - Man, Samuel: ms volume, "A Coppy of Some Sermons by the Revd Samuel Man," with a few pages of notes by descendants; printed genealogy of Man family, 1701-1707, 1789, 1800, n.d (Box 13, Folder 177)
        - [Massachusetts Federalists]: ms, "On the Election of S. Phillips Esqr. to the office of Lieut. Governor,", undated (Box 13, Folder 178)
        - Pilgrim's medal and ms note, in Greek, from the Greek convent of St. Catharine, Mt. Sinai, undated (Box 13, Folder 179)
        - Society for the support of the Panoplist and Missionary Magazine: constitution (ms copy), undated (Box 13, Folder 180)
    - Park, Harrison Greenough
      - School exercise, undated (Box 14, Folder 181)
    - Park, Marion Edwards, 1875-1960
      - Correspondence
        - Baker, Christina (Hopkinson), 1920 (Box 14, Folder 182)
        - Briggs, Le Baron Russell, 1920 (Box 14, Folder 183)
        - Cellinson, Annie C.E., 1906 (Box 14, Folder 184)